Helen Paull Kirkpatrick Papers, 1930-1998
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Helen Paull Kirkpatrick papers
1930 - 1998
Kirkpatrick, Helen Paull
MS 103
13 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Journalist. The Kirkpatrick papers include extensive correspondence to her family while serving as a foreign correspondent in Europe. Included are her views of Europe just before the outbreak of World War II; the air raids in London; Allied Headquarters in North Africa; campaigns in Algiers, Italy, and Corsica; the armistice in Paris; post-war Germany and Europe; the Nuremberg Trials; and the Council of Foreign Ministers in Moscow. Notable correspondents include Adlai Stevenson, Katharine Graham, Dean Acheson, Stewart Alsop, Styles Bridges, J. William Fulbright, General George C. Marshall, and Abe Ribicoff. Materials include broadcast scripts, lectures, published writings, diaries, photographs, and scrapbooks.
Helen Kirkpatrick was born October 18, 1909, in Rochester, NY, daughter of Lyman B. and Lyde Paull Kirkpatrick. She graduated from the Master's School, Dobbs Ferry, New York, in 1927 and from Smith College in 1931. In 1932, following postgraduate work at the University of Geneva, she became an assistant buyer at R. H. Macy & Co. in New York City. She married Victor H. Polacheck, Jr. in 1934. They were divorced in 1936. Between 1935 and 1937 Kirkpatrick worked in Geneva and England. During that time she was a writer, then editor, of Research Bulletin published by the Foreign Policy Association; research assistant for the Geneva Research Center (Foreign Policy Association) editing their "Geneva: A Monthly Review of International Affairs"; and correspondent for the New York Herald Tribune, Manchester Guardian, and London Daily Telegraph. Together with Victor Gordon-Lennox of the Daily Telegraph and Graham Hutton of the Economist she started the weekly Whitehall News Letter, which analyzed current state of European affairs. She was diplomatic correspondent for London Sunday Times in 1938 during the Munich crisis. Kirkpatrick expanded her views into two books, This Terrible Peace (1938) and Under the British Umbrella (1939).
As the war approached in 1939 Kirkpatrick began her career as a foreign correspondent. During the war she came to know many important figures in the European theatre. She traveled extensively under dangerous conditions and was respected and trusted for her political acumen and integrity. She was hired by the Chicago Daily News in 1939 and from their London office she covered the London blitz and the campaigns in Algiers, Italy, and Corsica (1943-45). She was the first correspondent after D-Day assigned to the headquarters of French forces inside France. She entered Paris in August 1944 riding in a tank of General Leclerc's 2nd Armored Division. As foreign correspondent for the New York Post, she covered the Nuremberg Trials and Council of Foreign Ministers in Moscow (1946-48). During the late 1940s she was with the Washington Bureau of the Post and was Chief of the Office of Information of the Economic Co-operation Administration's mission to France (1949-51). Between 1949 and 1953 she worked for the State Department with Voice of America, the Economic Cooperation Administration and as Public Affairs Advisor to the Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs (1951-53). In 1953 she become assistant to the president of Smith College. In 1954 she married Robbins Milbank.
Following her retirement in 1955, she was engaged in many civic activities including the Democratic Party, Citizens Advisory Committee to the Attorney General on Crime Prevention (1956-59), Public Advisory Committee for Trade Negotiations (1964), the League Of Women Voters, and the Harvard University Board of Overseers. Kirkpatrick received the French Medallion de la Reconnaissance (1945), French Legion of Honor (1947), U.S. Medal of Freedom (1947), an honorary degree from Smith College (1948), and Rockefeller Public Service Award (1953). Following the death of her husband in 1985, she moved to Williamsburg, Virginia, where she died on December 29, 1997.
The Kirkpatrick Papers consist of 5 linear feet of correspondence, clippings, writings, photographs, scrapbooks, memorabilia, and biographical material dating from 1930 to 1998. It is a well balanced collection that documents both her personal and professional lives. Of particular interest in these papers is Kirkpatrick's extensive correspondence to her family from overseas. She kept scrapbooks over the years and these, plus articles in SERIES II, provide extensive evidence of her writing.
Notable correspondents include Adlai Stevenson, Katharine Graham, Dean Acheson, Stewart Alsop, Styles Bridges, J. William Fulbright, General George C. Marshall, and Abe Ribicoff.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Professional Activities
III. Correspondence
IV. Photographs and Scrapbooks
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any added restrictions.
History of the Collection
The papers were a gift of Helen Paull Kirkpatrick between 1983 and 1993.
Search Terms
Smith College--History--Sources; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945--Journalists--Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945--Women--Personal narratives, American; War correspondents--Personal narratives, American; Women journalists--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971--Correspondence; Alsop, Stewart--Correspondence; Bridges, Styles, 1898-1961--Correspondence; Chase, Mary Ellen, 1887-1973--Correspondence; Duckett, Eleanor Shipley--Correspondence; Fulbright, J. William (James William), 1905- --Correspondence; Graham, Katharine, 1917- --Correspondence; Kirkpatrick, Helen Paull--Correspondence; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959--Correspondence; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910- --Correspondence; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1835-1914--Correspondence
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional material, including an oral history, is located in the Smith College Archives. There is also an oral history (1990), available online at the National Press Club Foundation Web site..
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1931-1979, 5 linear inches
  This series provides an overview of Helen Kirkpatrick's personal and professional lives. It consists of college and university related items (1931-79); wedding clippings and correspondence (1934, 1955); a short run of diaries (1932-36); unpublished poetry and essays (1931, n.d.); awards (1946-72); articles and clippings (1932-98); and memorabilia (1937-78).
  The Smith College material includes not only undergraduate records and memorabilia, but also general correspondence and items related to Kirkpatrick's life long relationship to the College. Additional Smith material can be found in material related to her position as Assistant to the President of Smith College (1953-55) and her relationship with the Smith College Alumnae Association (1948-81), both of which are included in SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL AND CIVIC ACTITIVIES. There are also Smith related photographs in SERIES IV. The diaries, consisting of a combination of typed originals, carbons, and handwritten material, relate to her life in Geneva (1932-36). Included with the articles and clippings which document her life and career from 1932 to her death in 1997 is a college term paper written about her in 1943. Memorabilia consists of passports, war correspondent items, financial material, and miscellaneous items.
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL AND CIVIC ACTIVITIES 1935-1981, 2.75 linear feet
  This series is divided into four subseries: Professional, Civic, Miscellaneous and freelance writings, and Lectures. The Professional subseries follows Kirkpatrick's professional employment beginning with her work for the Geneva Research Center in 1935 and ending with her position as Assistant to the President of Smith Co llege in 1955. Arranged chronologically, it contains printed material, correspondence, writings, and typescripts. Related material can also be found in SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND SCRAPBOOKS. The Geneva Research Center material consists of publications authored and/or edited by Kirkpatrick. Contained in the files of the three major newspapers for whom Kirkpatrick worked (The New York Herald Tribune, Chicago Daily News, and New York Post) are typescripts, correspondence, clippings, expense accounts, and financial material. The Chicago Daily News kept Kirkpatrick's mother appraised of her daughter's whereabouts and activities, so there are letters from her editor to Mrs. Kirkpatrick. There is material related to the three positions she held with the State Department before she resigned to become Assistant to Smith College President Benjamin Wright.
  The Civic subseries, arranged alphabetically, consists of correspondence, reports, memorabilia and clippings related to Kirkpatrick's civic activities mostly dated from her retirement from Smith College in 1955. Kirkpatrick led an active life supporting causes ranging from the environment to the Democratic Party. Her interest in higher education is reflected in her service not only to Smith College, but also Harvard, Dartmouth, Mills College, and the California State Coordinating Council for Higher Education. A friend of Adlai Stevenson, Kirkpatrick was a delegate to the 1956 Democratic Convention and an active member of the Democratic Party. There is correspondence from Stevenson in this section.
  Miscellaneous and freelance writings, arranged alphabetically, contains articles Kirkpatrick wrote for various newspapers and magazines (1936-68); book reviews and letters to the editor (1939-80); scripts of her broadcasts (1944-60); miscellaneous publications (1930-80); and her two books, This Terrible Peace (1939) and Under the British Umbrella (1938).
  The final subseries, Lectures, reflects Kirkpatrick's active lecture schedule (1937-80). It contains clippings, correspondence, bills, contracts, and schedules.
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE 1930-1982, 7.5 linear inches
  This series contains Professional and Personal correspondence to and from Kirkpatrick.
  The Professional correspondence (1946-82) is arranged alphabetically. Kirkpatrick knew many well known figures in government and she wrote many letters to members of Congress commenting on the issues of the day. There are responses to her from many of these people. Many of her professional associates were also personal friends.
  The bulk of the Personal correspondence consists of letters Kirkpatrick wrote to her family, which she did often and in much detail. These letters (1930-50) are of particular interest because they not only describe her personal and professional life, but also provide rich descriptions of her surroundings. Included are her views of Europe in the late 1930s just before the outbreak of World War II; air raids in London (1939-42); Allied Headquarters in North Africa (1943); France, particularly the armistice in Paris (1944); and post war Germany and Europe (1946-47). She socialized with many important people who are part of the life she describes.
  Her letters with friends (1931-68) reflect her wide and varied network. There is also correspondence in this file with many of her Smith College connections. Related to these are letters from author and Smith College professor, Mary Ellen Chase (1954-66), as well as several from Chase's friend Eleanor Shipley Duckett, keeping Kirkpatrick appraised of Chase's battle with breast cancer (1958-66).
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND SCRAPBOOKS 1930-1964, 1.25 linear feet
  The last series consists of approximately 55 photographs and scrapbook contents. It is divided into two subseries: Photographs and Scrapbooks.
  There are three sections of photographs: Smith College, Professional, and Miscellaneous. They are arranged chronologically within each section. The Smith College photographs consist of several undergraduate photos; they also document her honorary degree and other later Smith College activities. There are other related Smith College photographs located in the Smith College Archives. The second section contains photographs of Helen Kirkpatrick involved in many of her professional and civic activities (1936-64). The final section of miscellaneous photographs are not of Kirkpatrick. Six of the eight include Dean Acheson.
  The bulk of the scrapbooks (1936-44) contain clippings which have been photocopied for preservation purposes
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1931-1979
  - Smith College, 1931-79 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - University of Geneva/Institute Universitaire de Hautes Etudes Internationales, 1931-32 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Weddings, 1934, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1932-36 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Unpublished poetry and essays, 1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Awards, 1946-72 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles, 1932-98, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Memorabilia
    - Passports (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - War correspondent, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Expense accounts, fees, and taxes, 1939-44 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1937-78 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL AND CIVIC ACTIVITIES 1935-1981
  - Professional
    - Geneva Research Center
      - Geneva Special Studies, 1935-36 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Foreign Policy Reports, July 15, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Geneva: A Monthly Review of World Affairs, Jan-Aug 1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Geneva Newsletter, 1-4, 1936-37 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - New York Herald Tribune: typescripts, 1936-37 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Manchester Guardian, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Berkshire Eagle, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chicago Daily News, [see also SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND SCRAPBOOKS]
      - Correspondence, 1940-46 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
      - Writings
        - Typescripts from Ireland, 1941-42 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - Clippings
          - 1939-41 (Box 2, Folder 8-12)
          - 1942-46 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
          - Clippings containing additional text or variations from other Chicago Daily News clippings, 1939-44 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - New York Post
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous material, 1946-49 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Writings (typescripts), 1946-48 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
      - Clippings, 1946-48 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
      - Expense account, 1946-47 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - State Department
      - Voice of America, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Economic Cooperation Administration, 1949-51 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Public Affairs Office, 1949-53 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Smith College Assistant to the President
      - Talks and speeches, 1953-55 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, memoranda, and memorabilia, 1953-55 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Civic
    - Board of Overseers of Harvard College, 1971-76 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - California State Coordinating Council for Higher Education, 1960-62 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Conference on College Women in England and the United States, Bellagio, Italy, 1965, [see also SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND SCRAPBOOKS] (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Dartmouth Arts Council, 1967-71 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Democratic Party
      - Adlai Stevenson, 1949-65 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - California State Democratic Committee, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Advisory Committee on Foreign Policy, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Marshall Scholarship Commission, 1963-70 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Mills College Board of Trustees, 1960-62 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous activities, 1956-80 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - New Hampshire Conservation Commission, 1971-74 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - New Hampshire League of Woman Voters, 1967-73 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Public Advisory Committee for Trade Negotiations, 1964-66 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Smith College Alumnae Association, 1948-81 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous and freelance writings
    - Book reviews and letters to the editor, 1939-80 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Broadcasts: KNBC, BBC (scripts), 1944, 1958-60 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Colby Literary Quarterly, 1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "New Hampshire's Paper Tiger," Columbia Journalism Review
      - Correspondence, 1965-66 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Article, typescript, research material, 1963-66 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Keene (N.H.) Evening Sentinel, 1967-68 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - L'Ordre, 1938-39 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - London Daily Telegraph, 1936-37, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous articles and notes, 1930-81, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - The New Yorker, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - News Chronicle, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - This Terrible Peace (London, Rich and Cowan Ltd., 1939): photocopy and flyer (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Under The British Umbrella, What The English Are And How They Go To War (New York, Scribners, 1938) (Box 7)
  - Lectures
    - Texts, 1937-80, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Publicity, 1942-71 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, 1942-66 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1943-48 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Bills, contracts, and schedules, 1940-48, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE 1930-1982
  - Professional, A-Z, and unidentified, 1932-82, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Personal
    - To family, 1930-50 (Box 9, Folder 2-9)
    - Friends, 1931-68 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - From Mary Ellen Chase, 1954-66 (Box 10, Folder 2-7)
    - From Eleanor Shipley Duckett, 1958-66 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND SCRAPBOOKS 1930-1964
  - Photographs
    - Smith College
      - Junior Usher, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Easter vacation, Deerfield, MA, 1931 (Box 11)
      - Anne Booth, Harriet Loutrel, and Prof. Samuel Eliot, 1931 (Box 11)
      - Dewey House, 1931 (Box 11)
      - Honorary degree, 1948 (Box 11)
      - Julia Child, 1951 (Box 11)
      - President Thomas Mendenhall's inauguration, 1959 (Box 11)
      - Thomas Mendenhall in Alumnae House, 1960 (?) (Box 11)
    - Professional
      - David Woodward at Geneva airport, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - On the Queen Mary, 1937 (Box 11)
      - Ambassador and Mrs. Kennedy, 1939 (Box 11)
      - United States lecture tour, 1940 (Box 11)
      - Dorothy Thompson sailing from New York, 1940 (Box 11)
      - Mary Welsh, Dixie Tighe, Lee Miller, and Tania Daniell, 1941 (Box 11)
      - Hugh O'Connor, Joe Evans, and Mary Welsh (Hemingway), 1941 (Box 11)
      - Joe Evans, 1941 (Box 11)
      - Ed Beattie and Douglas Williams, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Mary Welsh (Hemingway), London, 1942 (Box 11)
      - Ireland, 1941 (Box 11)
      - First troops in Ireland, 1941 (Box 11)
      - Mary Welsh (Hemingway), London, 1942 (Box 11)
      - Belfast, 1942 (Box 11)
      - Northern Ireland with King and Queen and U.S. Army, 1942 (Box 11)
      - U.S. troops in Northern Ireland (2), 1942 (Box 11)
      - In General Strickland's jeep, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Capt. Robin en route to Capri, Italy, 1943 (Box 11)
      - Above Blue Grotto, Capri, Italy, 1943 (Box 11)
      - Europe, in combat uniform, 1944 (Box 11)
      - Presented with Medal of Freedom by General J. Lawton Collins (2), 1949 (Box 11)
      - ECA Agricultural Exhibit, 1949 (Box 11)
      - Pointoise, France, 1949 (Box 11)
      - "Washington Observer" (Voice of America), 1949 (Box 11)
      - Paul Child, Chief Exhibits (U.S.I.S. Paris), 1949-50 (Box 11)
      - Chamber of Commerce, St. Streune, 1950 (Box 11)
      - Barry Bingham, Chief of ECA Mission, 1950 (Box 11)
      - "Cooperative Caravan," Paris, 1950 (Box 11)
      - Mobile Caravan Exhibit, 1950 (Box 11)
      - French-American banquet, France (3), 1950 (Box 11)
      - Marseilles (2), 1950 (Box 11)
      - Prime Minister Pleven, Strasbourg Fair, 1950 (Box 11)
      - Ambassador Milton Katz, Minister Barry Bingham, ECA Capt. Pierre Lancelot - French Naval Attaché, 1950 (Box 11)
      - Meeting of Chiefs of Information for ECA missions in Europe, 1950 (Box 11)
      - U.S.I.S. offices, Paris, 1950 (Box 11)
      - Farewell party (4), 1951 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Press conference, U.S. Embassy, Vienna, 1951 (Box 11)
      - Harold Kaplan (Deputy Chief of Information, ECA, Paris), 1951 (Box 11)
      - General and Mrs. Robert McClure, Edward Barrett, Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs, 1951 (Box 11)
      - Dean Acheson at the American Embassy, 1952 (Box 11)
      - First official visit of U.S. Secretary State to Austria, 1952 (Box 11)
      - Lisbon, 1952 (Box 11)
      - Robbins Milbank and President Tano Jodai, Tokyo, Japan, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Conference on College Women in England and the United States, Bellagio, Italy, 1965 (3) (Box 11)
      - With young child in front of ECA, undated (Box 11)
      - In uniform (4), undated (Box 11)
      - Portrait, undated (Box 11)
      - State Department (16), undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous
      - U.K. delegate, Mr. Eden at Lisbon NATO conference, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Dean Acheson
        - Pearsons, Schumann, Eden, (NATO conference), 1952 (Box 11)
        - Berlin, 1952 (Box 11)
        - Mayor Reuter, Berlin, 1952 (Box 11)
        - Mrs. McCloy (2), Berlin, 1952 (Box 11)
      - Edmund G. Brown, undated (Box 11)
    - Scrapbooks
      - 1936-39 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Book reviews of This Terrible Peace and Under the British Umbrella, Lecture tour, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - 1940 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Chicago Daily News, 1939-40 (part 1 and 2) (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
      - 1940-41 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - 1941-42 (part 1 and 2) (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
      - 1941-45 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - 1943 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - 1943-44 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - 1944-45 (Chicago Daily News) (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
      - 1944-45 (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
      - 1944-46 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Chicago Daily News: advertisements, circa 1940s (Map-case Flat File)
  - Mounted clippings: "War and a Women," circa 1940s (Map-case Flat File)